hey everyone welcome back to the store
score automation playlist and today we
are going to continue with the second
part of the Excel engine now in the
previous session I showed you how you
can compare to Excel files which are
basically existing files but what about
the other functions like if you want to
open an Excel file if you want to close
it if you want to input some values into
the Excel file or if you want to verify
uh some values from the Excel sheet
right so these are the common functions
which you perform with an Excel during
your automation
and all of these functions are already
defined in the t-box modules uh in Tosca
okay so you can find it in the standard
subset where we found the compare Excel
module uh all the other modules are also
present
so let's see what are these modules and
how you can basically use this modules
okay
so uh I've already created a test case
called create Excel and inside this I
have you can see I have uh used couple
of modules from the Excel worksheet okay
and basically this will do uh first is
to open an Excel workbook okay then I'm
creating an Excel worksheet I am
defining Excel range I am manipulating
the Excel range and then I'm closing the
Excel workbook right so we'll understand
uh what are all these modules and what
they exactly do okay the t-box edit file
is just
um to delete any existing files before I
create a new Excel worksheet okay
now to add these modules is pretty much
the same away you add any module okay so
go ahead and search for t-box Excel and
that should pop up all the modules which
are present uh in Tosca okay
and part of the standard subset so uh we
will be looking at few of them if not
all okay so the first one which I want
to explain you uh is the t-box open
Excel workbook module okay and what it
exactly does is it allows you to open an
Excel file okay which is also a workbook
it can contain several worksheets okay
let's see what uh what all uh module
attributes you need to pass in order to
do this okay
so I'm going to close this as I said I
have already created uh this module
and in this uh the three most important
attributes are workbook name path and
the create new whether you want to
create a new workbook or you want to
read an existing workbook okay so you
can do both with this particular module
okay so you can open an existing file or
you can even create a new file in my
case I'm creating a new uh workbook okay
so I'm giving it a name employee data
and the path
um it's ctraining employee dot xlsx so
it will be creating this EMP
Excel Excel sheet okay and inside this I
have a bug book name which is employee
data okay
and then create new so either you can
set it to true or you can set it to
false okay
if you want to make it a password
protected you can give the password here
or if you want to open it as read-only
you can also select true or false
okay so these are all the attributes
which you need to use for open Excel
workbook and as I said this can be used
to both open an existing sheet or create
a new sheet
so the next module which you want to
look at is the create Excel worksheet
okay and in this so you can create a
worksheet if your worksheet is not
present or you want to create a new
worksheet okay
so here if I open this particular module
you need to provide the workbook name
and make sure the workbook name is
exactly the same which you have provided
while opening the workbook okay so
workbook name will remain same during
the complete test case
uh worksheet name you need to provide a
new worksheet name okay so I've given it
EMP uh worksheet order which means uh
where you want to create the sheet okay
so the position of the sheet it can be
first it can be any number you can
specify first or last okay so I have
specified it first so this sheet will
always be created as the first sheet in
the workbook okay
so this is open and then create Excel
worksheet and then comes the Define
excel range okay
so this module Define excel range allows
you to define a certain data range that
you want to steer from the Excel sheet
okay and mind you this step is mandatory
for every test case where you want to
manipulate any particular data range
okay so this is basically like selecting
any particular
um Excel sheet and then selecting a data
range right so if I'm selecting some
cells that's my data range okay so my
data range would be A1 and to B4 okay
and if I've got more data then I'll be
selecting like this okay so you have to
take the first cell which is A1 and the
last cell which is B4 okay so this is
the range we uh defined in an Excel
sheet okay same thing we are doing uh in
the cross cut test case okay we need to
define a certain data range we are
giving the range a particular name so
that we can refer it back
we are using the same sheet name and the
same workbook name which we have created
earlier okay in this data range then I
will be selecting a starting cell and
the ending cell okay
don't worry about this we can select any
particular uh and cell okay if you want
to continue creating more records you
can put some random value here or some
higher value okay so if you want to
create 40 records maybe or 49 records
then the answer will be 50 right
similarly you can put any range here
okay
so that's defining the Excel range and
the next step is to uh maybe you want to
manipulate or you want to input some
values into that particular range of
your or into your cells okay or you want
to verify something so you need to use
this particular module D box Excel range
manipulation
so here we need to provide the range
name okay so we have already defined
that in the previous step okay employee
data is our range name
so we'll be providing it here and then
inside that range we can create our data
table okay so inside this data table you
can see here I am creating some new
values or I am inputting some new values
okay so the first value is my header so
I have selected header here okay and
then uh the first
cell okay so this is the header row and
then the first cell or the first uh
column would be my header name okay so I
have given it full name and then the
cell to or the column 2 would be my
salary okay so I'm basically
uh structuring or creating this
particular Excel sheet which we are
going to create in this test case you
can see here it has got basically uh two
first header okay full name and salary
and then the values okay two rows and
then another total salary
which has got a value so this is the
sheet which I am creating with my test
case okay and if you come here you will
see that
um
this is my header values this is my
first row okay
these are the values you can see here I
am also using buffer to buffer this
amount one okay this this amount and
then in the second row again the values
and again I'm buffering this particular
value okay because I want to perform
some calculations later on
and then in the third row you can see
total salary and then I'm entering some
salary okay
and here again I am verifying it
obviously you can do it in a separate
test case okay that would be recommended
but uh for this demo purpose I have used
the same uh row number to with that
particular cell and I put a verification
step here okay so here you can see I
have used a math calculation okay uh
function and inside this I am then using
the buffer values amount 1 and amount
two I am summing it up and whatever uh
the result would be from this
calculation should be same as what is
present here okay so this is a
verification I am performing
okay so this is all you can do you can
input values you can buffer values you
can verify your values uh in your cells
from the Excel range you have defined
okay so all this can be done with this
Excel range manipulation module
and the last step is to close the Excel
workbook here you can do two functions
okay one you are closing the workbook
and the second you can also save it okay
so that is the same option you can set
it to true and false
uh you have to give the path okay
and then you have to
name the workbook which is employee data
okay so whatever we have defined earlier
the same name will be here okay
okay so I need to correct this uh Excel
path this should be EMP
and you can also give a separate path if
you want to save it somewhere else okay
and you can also save as type okay so
there is an option save as type here you
can see there are all the different
formats which you can read and write or
save and this using this particular
module okay so there is Excel workbook I
can save this as a PDF directly
okay and all the different txt CSV so
any any file format you can use to save
this as that particular type you can
also open different Excel types if you
are using Okay using this particular
module
some of the other t-box modules which
are available
and this
so let me show you that so we have seen
a file compare so that is a run Excel
macro so using this you can basically
run a macro which is present on your
Excel sheet okay so using this module
you can do that you can clear the Excel
range so if you want to clear your
previous range whatever you have
inputted into the cells if you want to
clear all those values you can use this
module
so Define we have seen manipulation we
have seen open close create so all of
this we have seen you can also delete an
Excel worksheet and you can also update
an Excel worksheet okay so if multiple
sheets in your Excel then you can delete
and update worksheets using this modules
okay
so these are all the modules which are
available
for the Excel engine okay and it could
be used for any kind of functions which
you want or operations which you want to
perform on Excel sheets okay
so let me go ahead and close this now
and let's go ahead and run this
particular test case okay let's see if
it works
so as you can see the test case has
passed okay and if I go ahead and look
at the results in the Excel range
manipulation specifically we have
encrypted some values right and if you
go into the verification step
you will see the buffer has also worked
this buffered the value into this amount
one and it is also verified okay so
expected value versus the actual value
right
so that's how you can perform all the
different operations on Microsoft Excel
using this particular modules or using
all of these different modules which are
present uh in the Excel
engine of Tosca and finally let me also
show you whether it has created the file
as we have defined it in our test case
so let's go here under this our sheet
name was EMP if you remember and if I
open this you will see uh exactly the
same data which we have created in our
test case Okay so the header names the
data values and index some calculation
okay which we are verifying this
particular value
so that's our Excel sheet which was
created with that particular test case
using all the different modules of the
Excel engine
so that's all for this video hope you
enjoyed it and you learned something new
today uh if you have any questions leave
it in the comment section
um keep watching our Channel as lots of
other videos are coming up if you want
to continue learning Tosca and other
automation tools